<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc='yes' ?><!-- add table of contents -->
<?rfc editing='yes' ?><!-- add paragraph numbering -->
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?><!-- use references like [ABC] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs='no'?><!-- sort the references alphabetically -->
<?rfc linkmailto='no'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc comments='yes'?><!-- print crefs -->
<?rfc inline='yes'?>
<?rfc-ext parse-xml-in-artwork='yes' ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<rfc ipr='trust200902'
  docName='draft-hansen-rfc-use-of-pdf-00' category='info' >
  <front>
    <title abbrev='PDF for RFCs'>PDF for an RFC Series Output Document Format</title>
    <author initials='T.' surname='Hansen' fullname='Tony Hansen' role='editor'>
      <organization>AT&amp;T Laboratories</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Ave. South</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <code>07748</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tony+rfc2pdf@maillennium.att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
      <organization>Adobe Systems</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>345 Park Ave</street>
	  <city>San Jose</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>95110</code>
	  <country>USA</country>
	</postal>
        <email>masinter@adobe.com</email>
        <uri>http://larry.masinter.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='M.' surname='Hardy' fullname='Matthew Hardy'>
	  <organization>Adobe Systems</organization>
	  <address>
		<postal>
		  <street>345 Park Ave</street>
		  <city>San Jose</city>
		  <region>CA</region>
		  <code>95110</code>
		  <country>USA</country>
		</postal>
		<email>mahardy@adobe.com</email>
	  </address>
    </author>
    <date />
    <area>RFC Design Team</area>
    <keyword>Requests for Comment</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	This document focuses on the requirements for the PDF
	rendering of RFCs in the RFC Series, as outlined in RFC
	6989. It also discusses the use of PDF for Internet Drafts,
	and available or needed software tools for producing and
	working with PDF.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t> The RFC Series is evolving, as outlined in <xref
      target='RFC6949'/>. Future documents will use an archival format
      of XML with renderings in various formats, including PDF.  </t>

      <t> PDF has a wide range of capabilities and alternatives; not
      all PDFs are "equal". For example, visually similar documents
      could be scanned or rasterized images, include text layout
      options, hyperlinks, embedded fonts, digital signatures.  This
      document explains the options and also makes recommendations for
      choices, both for the RFC series and also Internet Drafts.</t>

      <t> The PDF format and the tools to manipulate it are
      not as well known as those for other formats. This document
      discusses some of the processes for creating and using PDFs
      and both open source and commercial products.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='History and current use of PDF with RFCs and Internet Drafts'>
      <section title='RFCs'>
	<t>The RFC series has for a long time accepted Postscript
	renderings of RFCs, either in addition to or instead of the
	text renderings of those same RFCs.  These have usually been
	produced when there was a complicated figure or mathematics
	within the document.  For example, consider the figures and
	mathematics found in RFCs 1119 and RFC 1142, and compare the
	figures found in the text version of RFC 3550 with those in
	the Postscript version.  The RFC editor has provided a PDF
	rendering of RFCs. Frequently, this has been a print of the
	text file that does not take advantage of any of the broader
	PDF functionality, although, if there was a Postscript version
	of the RFC, the RFC editor would use that to generate a PDF
	instead.</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Internet Drafts'>
	<t>In addition to PDFs generated and published by the RFC
	editor, the IETF tools community has also long supported PDF
	for Internet Drafts.  Most RFCs start with Internet Drafts,
	edited by individual authors.  The Internet drafts submission
	tool at https://datatracker.ietf.org/submit/ accepts PDF and
	Postscript files in addition to the (required) text submission
	and (currently optional) XML.  If a PDF wasn't submitted for a
	particular version of an Internet Draft, the tools would
	generate one from the Postscript, HTML, or text.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title='Options and Requirements for PDF RFCs'>
      <t>This section lays out the options and requirements for PDFs produced by
      the RFC editor for RFCs. These are in two sections:
      "Visible" requirements are related to how the PDF appears when
      it is viewed with a PDF viewer. "Internal Structure" requirements
      affect the ability to process PDFs in other ways, but do not
      change the way the document looks.</t>
      <t>In many cases, the choice of PDF requirements is heavily
      influenced by the utility of available tools to create
      PDFs. Most of the discussion of tooling is to be found in
      <xref target='tooling'/>.</t>

      <section title='"Visible" requirements'>
	<t> PDF supports rich visible layout of fixed-sized pages.
	</t>
	<section title='General visible requirements'>
	  <t> For a consistent 'look' of RFC and good style, the PDFs
	  produced by the RFC editor should have a clear, easy-to-read
	  style. They should print well on the widest range of
	  printers, and look good on displays of varying
	  resolution.</t>
	</section>
	<section title='Page size, margins, headings'>
	  <t>PDF files are laid out for a particular size
	  of page, margins, and any headers and footers
	  part of the layout. Recommendations or ideas
	  for further study:
	  <list style='hanging'>
	    <t hangText='Page size'>
	      US Letter page size, but margins chosen so it will
	      print and look good on A4 paper.
	    </t>
	    <t hangText='Margins'>
	      The smallest margin consistent with above requirements.
	    </t>
	    <t hangText='Headings'>
	      The same information from the text version
	      of the document, but set in a smaller font
	      in a lighter color.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title='Similarity to other outputs'>
	  <t>There is some advantage to having the PDF files look like
	  the text or HTML renderings of the same document.  There are
	  several options even so. The PDF
	  <list style='numbers'>
	    <t>could look like the text version of the document, or</t>
	    <t>could look like the text version of the document but
	    with pictures rendered as pictures instead of using their
	    ASCII-art equivalent, or</t>
	    <t>could look like the HTML version.</t>
	  </list>
	  (Note that numbers 1 and 2 are what are currently produced by the RFC
	  Editor on their web site.)
	  </t>
	  <t>Recommendation: the PDF rendition should look like the HTML
	  rendition, at least in spirit -- for example, visually
	  searching or scanning should be facilitated. The typeface
	  and size for printing should be chosen.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Typeface choices">
	  <t> A PDF may refer to a font by name, or it may use an
	  embedded font.  When a font is not embedded, a PDF viewer
	  will attempt to locate a locally installed font of the same
	  name.  If it can not find an exact match, it will find a
	  "close match".  If a close match is not available, it will
	  fallback to something.  This is highly implementation dependent.</t>
	  <t>Recommendation: for consistent viewing, all fonts should
	  be embedded.  </t>
	  <t>In addition, since the HTML version of the document is
	  being visually replicated, the font(s) chosen should have
	  both variable width and constant width components, as well
	  as bold and italic representations.</t>
	  <t> Few fonts have glyphs for the entire repertoire of
	  Unicode characters; for this purpose, the PDF generation
	  tool may need a set of fonts and a way of choosing them.</t>
	  <t> Recommendation: ... TBD ...</t>
	  <t> For readability, the main body text should be in a serif
	  font and the headings in a sans-serif font. </t>
	  <t> Code, BNF, and other text could use a fixed-width
	  font to aid in insuring alignment, e.g., in BNF.</t>
	</section>
	<section title='Hyperlinks'>
	  <t>PDF supports hyperlinks both to sections of the same
	  document and to other documents.</t>
	  <t>Recommendation: All hyperlinks available in the HTML
	  rendition of the RFC should also be visible and active in the
	  PDF produced.</t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section title='"Invisible" options and requirements'>
	<t>There are many things going on under the cover:
	<list style='symbols'>
	  <t>What is usable in an RFC rendered as PDF?</t>
	  <t>Where can we improve on the past?</t>
	  <t>Where must we improve?</t>
	  <t>What must be supported in PDF?</t>
	</list>
	These all turn into requirements for the conversion tools that
	are used to generate the PDF rendering of the visible
	representation.</t>
	<t>
	  The areas we'll discuss are oriented around:
	  <list style='numbers'>
	    <t>Text Structure</t>
	    <t>Unicode support</t>
	    <t>Metadata</t>
	    <t>Document Structure</t>
	    <t>Tagged PDF</t>
	    <t>Extractable Sections</t>
	    <t>Document Signatures</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<section title='Text Structure'>
	  <t> The contents of a PDF file can be represented in many
	  ways.  The PDF file could be generated:
	  <list style='symbols'>
	    <t>as an image of the visual representation, such as a picture of the word 'IETF'</t>
	    <t>placing individual characters in position on the page, such as saying "put an 'F' here", then "put an 'T' before it",
	    then "put an 'E' before that", then "put an 'I' before that" to render the word 'IETF'
	    </t>
	    <t>placing words in position on the page, such as keeping the word 'IETF' would be kept together,
	    and</t>
	    <t>using higher-level constructs for sets of words,
	    such as keeping the sentence 'The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) supports the Internet.' together as a sentence.</t>
	  </list>
	  All of these end up with the same visual representation of the output.
	  However, each level has trade offs for auxiliary usage of the format.
	  For example, when using an annotation tool to review a PDF file, it is harder to place a comment
	  on a location within an image compared to attaching a comment to a given word.
	  Attaching a comment to a set of words (such as a bracketed set of words) is easier when using higher-level constructs.
	  Another example where higher-level constructs are needed are for accessibility purposes.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Requirement: the tools that are chosen must use the higher-level constructs for text structure.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title='Unicode Support'>
	<t>
	  Unicode is being fully supported, so the RFC PDF format must similarly have full support for Unicode.
	  While Unicode is not required by PDF, certain PDF profiles require its support.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Requirement: PDF files generated must have the full text, exactly as it appears in the original XML for text, or within SVG for images.
	  (What about text in image illustrations?)
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Metadata Support'>
	<t>
	  Metadata encodes information about the document authors, the document series, date created, etc. using
	  the RDF Dublin core (and other elements).
	  Having this metadata within the PDF file allows it to be extracted by the rendering tools.
	  It can also include additional information such as pointers to where the document can be found on the RFC Editor web site.
	</t>
	<t>PDF supports embedded metadata using XMP. </t>
	<t>
	  Recommendation: The PDFs generated should have all of the metadata from the XML version embedded directly as XMP metadata, including the author and date information, 
	  set the document series, and a URL for where the document can be retrieved.
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Document Structure Support'>
	<t>
	  The section structure of an RFC can be mapped into the PDF elements for the document structure.
	  This will allow the bookmark feature of PDF readers to be used to quickly access sections of the document.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Requirement: The section structure of an RFC must be mapped into the PDF elements for the document structure.
	  This would include section headings for the boilerplate sections such as the Abstract, Status of the Document,
	  Table of Contents, and Author Addresses.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title='Tagged PDF'>
	<t>
	  ... say more about the use of alternative texts for images,
	  tagging text spans and giving them an ID,
	  and
	  providing replacement texts for symbols and images
	  <vspace/>...<vspace/>
	  hyperlinks within the document,
	  hyperlinks to external locations,
	  <vspace/>...<vspace/>
	  where should hyperlinks to RFCs point? to the info page for the RFC? to the PDF version of the RFC?
	  <vspace/>...<vspace/>
	  similar questions on references to internet drafts
	  <vspace/>...<vspace/>
	  a role-map should be provided here to map the logical tags found in the RFC XML to the standard tagset for PDF.  This would be included in the generated PDF.
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title='Embedded Files'>
	<section title='Extractable Code Segments and Artwork'>
	  <t>
	    It has been suggested that the source input for code
	    segments (e.g., ABNF, C code, MIBs) be extractable from
	    the PDF.  This capability might be supported through other
	    mechanisms from the XML source files, but could also be
	    supported within the PDF.  PDF/A-2 (based on PDF release
	    1.7) allows for the embedding of some file formats, while
	    PDF/A-3 adds support for arbitrary files to be embedded.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title='Extractable XML source'>
	  <t>
	    Another suggestion that has been made is that the XML
	    input file itself could be embedded within the PDF.  This
	    would make the PDF file totally self-referential.
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section title='Document Signatures'>
	<t>
	  PDF has supported file signatures since PDF 1.2.  It has
	  been suggested that the PDF files be signed by the RFC
	  Editor on creation.  This would allow the signatures to be
	  authenticated.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Recommendation: The RFC PDF documents created by the RFC
	  Editor should be digitally signed.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Recommendation: Internet drafts do not need to be digitally signed.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section title='Tooling' anchor='tooling'>
    <t>This section will talk about tools for creating, manipulating, transforming PDF files, including those currently in use by the RFC editor and Internet drafts, as well as outlining available PDF tools for various processes.</t>
    <t>during either phase: generation.</t>
    <t>during I-D phase: xml2rfc, of course for authors. Copy from PDF files? Review and comment. Digital Signature tools. Comparing two PDF files (versions). </t>
    <t>
    During RFC publishing, xml2rdf. Editing of PDF to correct layout errors. Nits checking, checking conformance with PDF/a and PDF/ua.</t>
    </section>
    <section title='Picking a PDF Profile'>
      <t>There are profiles of PDF for specific purposes: PDF/UA and PDFA3 etc.
      </t>
      <t>Recommendation: use PDF/UA and also PDF/A3.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <!-- references title='Normative References'>
    </references -->
    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3778' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6949' ?>
    </references>
      <section title='A Synopsis of PDF Format History'>
	<t>
	  <xref target='RFC3778'/> contains some history of PDF.
	  This is a capsule view, plus additional information on events that have occurred since the publication of <xref target='RFC3778'/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The Portable Document Format (PDF) family of document formats was invented by Adobe Systems in the early 1990s.
	  At the time, it was a proprietary format that underwent a variety of revisions that matched the release of different versions of
	  the Adobe Acrobat products.
	  For example, Acrobat 1 supported PDF version 1.0, Acrobat 2 supported PDF version 1.1, Acrobat 5 supported PDF version 1.4, etc.
	  <eref target='http://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive.html'/>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Each release (and extension level) introduced new features.
	  For example, (1.0) character, word and image rendering, externally-referenced or embedded fonts, (1.1) passwords, encryption,
	  device-independent color, (1.2) interactive forms, unicode, signatures, compression, (1.3) web semantic capture, embedded files,
	  Adobe javascript, (1.4) metadata streams, tagged PDF, (1.5) controllable hiding of sections, slideshows, (1.6) 3D artwork,
	  OpenType font embedding, linking into embedded files, and (1.7) video and audio support.
	  After release 1.7, additional Extension Levels have been introduced.
	  Each release also provided enhancements to the previous support.
	  For example, encryption was introduced in 1.1, but AES encryption wasn't supported until 1.7 extension level 3.
	  A PDF reader for PDF 1.1 is not able to read and display a PDF 1.7 file, but a PDF reader for PDF 1.7 can also handle all
	  previous versions of PDF.
	  The wikipedia page at  <eref target='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF'/> has a nice summary table going into further details.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Certain profiles or subsets of PDF have been standardized.
	  PDF/X (X for Exchange), PDF/A (A for Archive), PDF/E (E for Engineering), PDF/VT (VT for Variables and Transactions), and PDF/UA
	  (UA for Universal Access) all have ISO standards associated with them.
	  Of particular potential interest to the RFC community are PDF/A and PDF/UA.
	</t>
	<section title='PDF/A'>
	  <t>
	    PDF/A in turn has nuances, as there have been a couple updates to it and conformance levels within each version.
	    PDF/A-1 was based on PDF release 1.4.
	    PDF/A-2 was based on PDF release 1.7, and PDF/A-3 adds embedded arbitrary files.
	    PDF/A is considered a profile because it mandates that certain optional features be used.
	    At a high level, the conformance levels are B (basic), U (mandatory unicode mapping [not in PDF/A-1]) and A (accessible).
	    The requirements for conformance level A are that: the document structure must be represented within the PDF (e.g., section
	    headings, table cells, paragraph divisions), tagged PDF is used (e.g.,  element anchors) and that language tags be used where
	    appropriate.
	    When referring to PDF/A, you would refer to the version and conformance level.
	    So PDF/A-1A would be the profile for the Accessible conformance level of version 1 of PDF/A, which was based on PDF 1.4.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title='PDF/UA'>
	  <t>
	    The PDF/UA (Universal Access) profile is orthogonal to the other profiles, specifying user accessibility requirements.
	    It places some restrictions on the other profiles, such as requiring the use of higher-level constructs for the textual representation
	    and adds additional requirements for programatic access (think automatic readers for the blind).
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title='Additional Reading'>
	  <t>
	    <eref target='http://www.pdflib.com/fileadmin/pdflib/pdf/whitepaper/Whitepaper-Technical-Introduction-to-PDFA.pdf'/>
	    <eref target='http://www.pdfa.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/tn0003_metadata_in_pdfa-1_2008-03-128.pdf'/>
	    <eref target='http://www.pdfa.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/PDFA-in-a-Nutshell_1b.pdf'/>
	    <eref target='http://www.pdfa.org/2011/08/pdfa-%E2%80%93-a-look-at-the-technical-side/'/>
	    <eref target='http://pdf.editme.com/pdfa'/>
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
